Ken Bald Papers
Ken Bald Papers
1957-1970
Bald, Kenneth.
25 linear ft.
Primarily contains over 2,900 pieces of original artwork for the Judd Saxon and Dr. Kildare comic strips; as well as small quantities of correspondence, proofs, photographs, sketches, printed and published material.
148826
Biographical History
Kenneth "Ken" Bald (1920- ) is an American comic book and comic strip artist.
Ken Bald was born August 1, 1920 in New York City. Bald attended the Pratt Institute and landed a job at Jack Binder’s studio. After serving with the Marines during World War II, Bald went to work for Timely Comics. Bald worked on comic book characters including, Captain America, Bulletman, the Sub-Mariner and Miss America. Some of his work appeared under the pen name, K. Bruce.
In the 1950s, Bald switched from working on comic books to comic strips and Bald began drawing Judd Saxon for King Features Syndicate. In 1962, Bald started the Dr. Kildare strip, based on the popular television series starring Richard Chamberlain. Bald dropped Judd Saxon in 1963. Bald also created another television inspired comic strip, Dark Shadows, based on the gothic soap opera of the same name. That strip appeared from 1971 to 1972. In addition to comic art, Bald also worked as a commercial artist.
Ken Bald retired with the end of the Dr. Kildare strip in the 1980s.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Ken Bald Papers consists of one main series and four series with additional material about Bald's career as well as limited material about Bald's personal life.
Artwork (1957-1970) comprises the majority of the collection. Included are approximately 2,968 original comic strips for Judd Saxon (748 items) and Dr. Kildare (1,990 dailies, 230 Sundays). There are also two Dr. Kildare sketches: a portrait of Kildare and an operating room. The Judd Saxon strip features an xecutive turned detective Dr. Kildare strip is based on the television series.
Judd Saxon artwork measures 6 1/4" x 21". Dr. Kildare daily strips measure approximately 5 3/4" x 19" with some smaller at 5 ½" x 17 ½". Sunday Dr. Kildare strips measure 16 1/4" x 23 ½". Daily strips do not have a logo with the name of either strip. Bald worked in pen and ink on illustration board. Zipatone screening was also used and some traces of blue pencil and watercolor are also visible. Corrections and notations appear on the strips in pencil. Some daily strips have engraver's date stamps on the back. Bald also pasted on some elements as many portions of the completed panels were drawn separately and pasted on to the completed panel.
Correspondence (1960-1966) consists of one folder of incoming correspondence. Correspondents include: Coulton Waugh, Cincinnati Enquirer employees and fans. Subjects include requests for cartoons and comments on the Dr. Sky Healer character (1964) from the Dr. Kildare strip.
Photos (1962-1964) contains one dozen snapshots of Bald, his wife and their daughter acting. There are also two Bald family photo Christmas cards.
Proofs (1964-1966) contains eighteen proof sheets for Dr. Kildare. Included are both color Sunday proofs and daily proof sheets.
Published and printed material (1962-1965) contains examples of Bald's commercial art, newspaper clippings, and promotional material for Dr. Kildare.
Arrangement of the Collection
Daily Judd Saxon strips are arranged chronologically. Dr. Kildare is divided into daily and Sunday strips and arranged chronologically. Correspondence is arranged chronologically.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Bald, Kenneth.; King Features Syndicate.; Dr. Kildare (comic strip); Judd Saxon (comic strip); American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Detective and mystery comic books, strips, etc.; Comic books, strips, etc. -- United States.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Kildare, Doctor (Fictitious character) -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Cartoons (humorous images); Comic strips.; Correspondence.; Proofs (printed matter); Photographs.; Cartoonists.; Commercial artists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Ken Bald, 1966, 1969-1971.
Inventory
- Artwork
  - Judd Saxon, 748 items; Click here for a detailed inventory.
    - Daily cartoons
      - 1957-Apr 1958 (Oversize 1)
      - May 1958-Jul 1959 (Oversize 2)
      - Aug-Dec 1959 (Oversize 3)
      - Jan-Jul 1960 (Oversize 4)
      - Aug 1960-Apr 1961 (Oversize 5)
      - May-Dec 1961 (Oversize 6)
      - Jan-May 1962 (Oversize 7)
      - Jun-Nov 1962 (Oversize 8)
  - Dr. Kildare, 2,220items; Click here for a detailed inventory.
    - Daily cartoons, 1,990 items
      - Jan 1962-Jun 1963 (Oversize 9)
      - Jul 1963-Feb 1964 (Oversize 10)
      - Mar-Jul 1964 (Oversize 11)
      - Aug-Dec 1964 (Oversize 12)
      - Jan-Jun 1965 (Oversize 13)
      - Jul-Dec 1965 (Oversize 14)
      - Jan-Jun 1966 (Oversize 15)
      - Jul-Dec 1966 (Oversize 16)
      - Jan-May 1967 (Oversize 17)
      - Jun-Sep 1967 (Oversize 18)
      - Oct 1967-Feb 1968 (Oversize 19)
      - Mar-Jul 1968 (Oversize 20)
      - Aug-Dec 1968 (Oversize 21)
      - Jan-May 1969 (Oversize 22)
      - Jun-Dec 1969 (Oversize 23)
      - Jan-Jun 1970 (Oversize 24)
      - Jul-Dec 1970 (Oversize 25)
    - Sunday cartoons, 230 items
      - 1964-Jun 1965 (Oversize 26)
      - Jul 1965-1966 (Oversize 27)
      - 1968 (Oversize 28)
      - 1969-1970 (Oversize 29)
    - Sketches, undated; 2 items; Dr. Kildare portrait and operating room scene (Oversize 30)
- Correspondence
  - Incoming correspondence, 1960-1966 (Oversize 30)
- Photos
  - Snapshots and Christmas cards, 1962-1964; 12 black and white photos, 2 photo Christmas cards of Bald and family, caption information on back (Oversize 30)
- Proofs
  - Dr. Kildare (color Sunday), May 31 1964; Oct 4 1964,; Nov 22 1964,; Dec 5 1965,; Sep 18 1966; 5 items (Oversize 30)
  - Dr. Kildare (daily), Feb 1964; May-Jun 1964,; Oct 1964,; Dec 1964,; Feb 1965,; Apr-May 1965,; Jul 1965,; Nov 1965,; 13 sheets (Oversize 30)
- Published and printed material
  - Commercial art, undated (Oversize 30)
    Air France Jet-Away Bibleland Holiday, Diamond Art Studio, General Hospital of Monroe County, Hertz, Sales Management, Vick Chemical Company
  - Dr. Kildare promotional material, 1962-1964 (Oversize 30)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1963-1965; one article about Bald, one Dr. Kildare daily comic strip clipping in French, two color Sunday clippings (Oversize 30)